Hello and welcome back to Lam Rim (LAM RIM).
We begin episode no.  9. I like
to call it
"A visit in the middle of the sun."  We
talked about
something that is big enough and strong enough.
It's like a nuclear bomb used to clean ketchup
off your shirt or something.
And I'm not exaggerating.
I want you to think like that.
Imagine...
Today is Independence Day in America.
I'm talking about Independence Day.  We
often go on picnics with our family.
It's the middle of summer.
And American kids will eat hot dogs
or hamburgers and put too much ketchup on them,
and a little drop of ketchup will jump out here.
Imagine that to clean it, mom sends the shirt or blouse into the middle of the sun
[Inaudible]
To clean a small drop of ketchup, of red ketchup.
I know it seems like a strange image,
but I want you to try to think about it.  I want you to
try to think about it.  I don't
know what we could compare it to.  I don't
know.
Just put something small in the middle of the sun, okay?
So we're going to visit the middle of the sun today.
And I'm happy to announce that we've just reached the third and final section of the lam rim.  The
Stepwise Path to Enlightenment.
Now we are about to move
into the activities of a bodhisattva.
We are about to move to the
way of thinking and acting of a bodhisattva,
who is the person with the highest goal.
@KYES BU CHEN PO
Which means a person with high purpose.
Those of you, especially those who have participated in this lam rim for the past ten years,
should be very happy that you survived
and that I survived to reach the last part.  We've
reached the last part.  It
's the last third.
Now, the mathematicians among you should calculate logically:
Geshe-la, you just said that we still have 25% to make of this lam rim.
So where does this last third come from?
And the answer is that the treatment
prescribed by Pabongka Rinpoche for the last two days
of the lam rim is too short.
His presentation on meditation
and the perception of emptiness,
which are the last two perfections of the six,
is not very long.
And I don't know what happened.  I mean
, sometimes-- it
's like the sponsor comes to him and says we're going to run out of food in two days.
Let's finish!
It's possible it's
a mystical message from Tara.
Maybe, I don't know,
maybe he had another meeting in another city.
But if you ask me, Pabongka Rinpoche
made the last two parts shorter because
Je Tsongkhapa included them in his great Lam Rim.
"The Great Book
of the Stages of the Path to Enlightenment,"
Lam Rim Chenmo
Tsongkhapa did such a good job that I think I
can see Pabongka Rinpoche saying,
"You see, I don't
have much reason to teach this part
because Tsongkhapa has already taught it
and done it in a tremendous way."
There are many, many stories about
Tsongkhapa who wrote these last two parts,
and I am very happy
because we will study them together.
So we will end this lam rim series
with amazing teachings on meditation and emptiness.
And that's why this part about the stages of the path for people who have bodhichitta,
for Bodhisattvas,
is not as long as it could have been.
So let's get started.
Let's read the Tibetan:
@ GSUM PA SKYES BU CHEN PO'I LAM GYI RIM
PAR BLO SBYANG BA LA
Let's train our hearts on the path to enlightenment
for highly motivated people --
people who are bodhisattvas.
@THEG CHEN GYI 'JUG SGO SEMS BSKYED KHO NAR BSTAN PA PHAN YON DANG BCAS PA
He says we will walk through this
way of life of a bodhisattva.  we
will go through it in three different stages.
Number one.
@ THEG CHEN GYI 'JUG SGO
If you wish to enter the path of a bodhisattva,
there is only one way to get there.
And this is by achieving a certain mental state.
If you want to become enlightened,
if you want to have a chance to become enlightened,
if you want to have a chance to help the world,
there is only one way: you
must attain bodhichitta.
You must obtain this desire to attain enlightenment
so that you can help countless beings.
Now, I want to talk about what countless means.
Bodhichitta aims at countless living beings.  It
doesn't target all the people in your city or all the people in your country or all the people on this planet.
Expand!
If we want to send the virus to the middle of the Sun,
if we want to visit the middle of the Sun, we
have to give up this idea that we are working
[only] for all the people on this planet.
We don't do that.
Give up this idea that we're trying to help
all the fish and all the birds and all the
land animals.
We don't do that.  That's not the point
.
We encompass the entire universe.
We [each] decide today, that I would like to help
every living creature in the universe.
Every little virus.
Bacteria.
Every whale.
Every human in the universe.
Going out at night in Sedona or outside of Sedona,
in Rim Rock is better.
And look at the stars and try to imagine.
First of all, you cannot practice the way of life of a bodhisattva
if you do not expand your mind towards this goal.
And if you really experience this fact,
-- which takes some practice,
if you really send your mind --
if you're really able to attain bodhichitta,
then the things you have to do in this world are nothing.  It does
n't mean anything.  It's something insignificant.
Helping all the people in this world means nothing.  It's
easy.
@PHAN YON DANG BCAS PA means
I want to tell you the benefits of such thinking.
This is the first stage.
@BYANG CHUB TU SEMS BSKYED PA'I TSUL
Second stage.
How do you reach this achievement?
Mental achievement?
How do you perceive the entire universe
and all beings in it?
And then develop love for them?
Is it possible?
This is the second stage.
Third stage.
@SEMS BSKYED NAS SPYOD PA LA SLOB TSUL LO
We will learn how to behave like a bodhisattva.
Once I have this aspiration to become a bodhisattva
what should I actually do?
How do I spend my daytime hours
if I want to act like a bodhisattva?
What to do?
What will my schedule be?  All
right.  This is the first oath.
@) DANG PO NI,
DE LTAR SKYES BU CHUNG 'BRING GI SKABS SU NGES 'BYUNG GI BSAM PAS KUN NAS BSLANGS
Now that we have gone through the steps on the path of people with low motivation and with average motivation,
at least you should have this feeling that
indeed this life is pain, indeed this life means problems.
The virus is just a way of emphasizing the obvious.
But it's always been like this.  There has
always been a virus called death.
This virus is the new one.  It's much smaller.
But at least now we're all thinking about him.
@ LHAG PA'I BSLAB PA GSUM LA 'BAD PAS
Then we should
work on the three extraordinary workouts.
Treat others well.
Spend time in meditation.
And then try to see
that things don't come by themselves.
@'BAD PAS RANG GCIG PUS
THAR BA'I GO 'PHANG
THOB TZAM DANG 'KHOR BA
LAS LDOG TZAM 'BYUNG
You can reach nirvana alone
and get out of the Wheel of Life.
If you practice these attitudes then you can, it is possible.
But I've learned that already, I'm done with it.
@ DE TZAM GYIS MI CHOG
But I don't want you to stop here.  I do
n't want you to stop here.  I want you
to take care of much more important things.  There
are much more important things to do.  Don't stop here.
@SPANG BYA THAMS CAD MA SPANGS
If you stick to what I have taught you so far,
you will not cleanse your heart
of all the unclean things there.
@ THOB BYA YON TAN
THAMS CAD KYANG YONGS SU MA RDZOGS PAS
and you would not attain
the highest
spiritual qualities you could attain.
@ MA RDZOGS PAS
Therefore,
@ RANG DON DANG,
GZHAN DON YANG NYI TSE BA LAS MI 'BYUNG
@NYI TSE BA is a very discouraging word here.
It's a very sad word here.
It is said that, you can work with these methods that I have taught you so far,
you can work with
all those meditations that I have taught you so far,
but the amount of good
that you will do for yourself and for others
is only a small amount of what you need to do.
@ NYI TSE BA means it's just a small amount
of what you should be doing.
And by the way, the most common use of this word is the Tibetan word for hell on earth.
Which is very strange.
So, it's a big hell where people can go.
But I always think of a person who had a car accident and the car exploded and burst into flames.
In the scriptures this is called
@NYI TSI BA'I DMYAL BA
A little piece of hell on this plane.  In this plane of reality.
And so this word @NYI TSI BA means just a small piece.
And here he says, do you want to help yourself
and help other people too?
All I've taught you so far for 10 years is
@NYI STI BA.
That's just a small part of what you could do, and now we're ready to start the serious stuff.
Well Geshe-la, why did I spend 10 years doing @NYI TSI BA, the small things?
Why didn't we go on to bigger things?
Because small things are a ladder
that helps you reach great things.  You ca
n't achieve great things
if you don't do the other two parts.
If you don't practice all the steps in the lam rim
in their correct order you will
never reach the part with the bodhisattva.
So, you can't say I don't want to.
Part of the bodhisattva way of life is mastering the lower path that helped you get here.
And never reject it.
You just have to grow out of it.
@MI 'BYUNG ZHING SLAR THEG CHEN
LA GZHI NAS 'JUG DGOS LA
This is an idea in Buddhism,
that as soon as you're ready
and as soon as you've gone through the path of preparation, you
should go straight to the
way of life of a Bodhisattva
because if you don't, you
'll have to do it again anyway, so
sooner or later, you'll have to get here.
This life may last.
Or it may be later in this life.
People come to me from time to time and say, "I'm going to take a break from this dharma.
I feel like I need to take a break.
I have other things to do right now.
I have a big project at work
or I have some family situations
and I need to take a break."
I remember once in India, I said to one of my teachers,
45 years ago,
I said, "I need to take a break," and he looked at me and said, "Yeah, okay, but you'll come back. You'll come
back because you have nowhere else to go. You'll come back
. You'll come back to this because you need to come back to this. Life will bring you back here."
Because that's life.  You need a lam rim.
Life will always bring you back to lam rim.
Unless you die.
And even so, it will bring you back later.
@ SLAR means you have to go back.
@ SLAR THEG CHEN LA GZHI NAS
@ GZHI NAS means you will waste a lot of time
if you have to go back.
You might as well do it now
instead of coming back to it later.  The
next image here
is a little bit of what I
want to do with you in this episode, in episode 9.
I call it "A Visit to the Middle of the Sun."
So, in this image...
I tried to find an image that suggested
what it would be like to have bodhichitta.
So, this image looks a little bit...
-- we say, Seiji and Tim --
we said it's a little bit New Age.  It
was apparently painted in Sedona, Arizona.  It
feels a little New Age but let me say something.
If you ever reach bodhichitta you
will feel it...
This image is very close.  This image is close up.  Can you leave it like that?  Just for a minute?
This image is not strange
and it is not something hippie.
When you achieve bodhichitta, true bodhichitta,
it feels very much like that.  You
might want to make a copy of this image.  I
already paid for it.
You could use it at home.  You could keep it at home.
You could keep an image like this.  Maybe you can put it
on your phone screen.
It's pretty close to what it feels like when you've reached bodhichitta.
So I'd like to take you on a little trip just for fun, maybe for five minutes.
Let's analyze what it feels like
when you first attain true bodhicitta.
So, we're not talking about trying
-- What's it called?  -- Partial bodhichitta.
Or try to feel like you have bodhichitta.
Let's talk about the real thing.
the day you will perceive emptiness directly
and experience bodhichitta directly.
Let's just go through it because it brings good luck.  And it's an
atomic bomb.
If you keep working on it, if you keep working on it
to feel what it feels like, if you keep listening to this part,
that will help destroy the virus.
I think it will help destroy the virus.  It's
like a nuclear weapon.
And the virus is like a ketchup stain.
So let's get started.
Let's try to imagine for five minutes
what it's like to reach bodhichitta.
Let's start.
Let's take ten slow breaths.
Focus on exhaling, long exhalations, don't worry about inhaling, your body will breathe.
So please imagine
that you have just perceived emptiness directly.
And you come out of that direct perception
and go back to what we can call normal meditation, which is not yet in the world.
You are in a deep state of meditation,
you are still on the pillow.  Your
eyes are closed.
Then, suddenly the image of your mother appears in front of your mind
.  It's your mother.
A very, very clear picture of your mother.  A vivid image.  She
really is your mother.
Maybe as you remember it best.
This is what it looks like right now.  He's looking at you
.  He
looks into your eyes.
Even though it feels like she's at the front of your mind, she's looking into your eyes.
With great love and also with a sense of need.
He really needs help.  He's in
trouble in some way.
Like they jumped off the Titanic or something
and they look at you with that look.
She says, "I need you, I need help."
And then you say out loud in your heart:
"Don't worry, mom, I'll take care of you."
And I will be strong enough to take care of you.  You do
n't have to worry.
I will have the power to help you
and I will.  I promise."
And then her image fades from your mind, and suddenly your father's image appears.
And you look at your father.
And he has that same look in his eyes. He's kind of
waiting. But he's also afraid.
So he looks at you like,
"Can you help me?"
In life, things get tough, life is tough right now.
And then you say, "Dad, don't worry.  I'll take care of this!
I am studying lam rim.
I study a lot about emptiness.
And I practically know that I will have the tools
to help you soon.
So don't worry.  I'll take care of this.  I'll take
care of this.  And
please: You do
n't have to be afraid.  You don't have to worry.
I know what to do and I do it.
Everything will be fine, so don't worry!"
And then it could be someone close to you, your
wife, your husband, or your children,
one of your children,
their image comes to mind.
Just their face.
And they look at you too, like, "Can you help me?  Things are bad, things are very bad!"
Things are terrible, there is no other hope.
"Can you help me?"
And you say:
"I can handle it, I'll take care of it.  I
can!  I
will have enough strength to take care of you.  You
really don't need to worry.  I know what's
happening.  I
know your situation.  I know what this
life is like.  I figured it out
.
and I will take full care of you.  You do
n't have to worry.  You
really don't need to worry.
I'll take care of you."
And then that face disappears, and you can start visualizing, one by one, the faces of people you know.
Close family members.
Uncles, aunts.
Brothers, sisters.
Nephews, nieces.
One by one, you visualize them
and comfort them.
And you say to them, "I really will take care of you.  You
have nothing to worry about."
And so, you go through all the people that you know.
All the people that you've ever met in your life.
Then you start with all the people that you haven't met and all the people in this world.
Start with your own neighborhood.
Go to the city, the entire city, and you know, it's not like you can cover the whole world.
But take one person from here and one person from there. Go to the
edge of this continent that you live on.
Go through everyone, every single one.
And then go on.
To other continents.
And in this way we'll go through all the people in this world.
Just sitting here.
And then you can start with the
animals in this world, the fish, for example. I'm
not talking about species of animals.
I'm talking about helping each individual animal.
Every animal is looking at you. Every animal is waiting.
Every animal is afraid.
Every animal gets your personal guarantee.
And you say, "I'll take care of this!  I will take care of you."
Imagine that you are going through every creature, all the little creatures at the bottom of the sea. The
little creatures in your blood.
Get to know each one of them.
Talk to them.
And when you are done with all the creatures in this world,
we will start with the ones in the next world.
But I don't know where the next world is.
Is it Alpha Centauri?
Maybe it's a few light years away.
Go there with your mind and start doing the same meditation
for all the people in that world.
And in this way we go through every world
in the entire universe.
And the karma of meeting
each one of the seven billion human beings
and trillions of other creatures on a planet.
And then visiting all the planets that exist. The countless planets.
Meeting every being there.
That is bodhichitta.
That is having the direct experience of bodhichitta.
For this episode, please
try to get this feeling. You
don't have to worry, you do
n't have to worry about your family.  You do
n't have to worry about your country.
And you don't have to worry about a world that's overwhelmed by a virus. These are small things!
By the way, we'll take care of them.
We're working on a much bigger project here. We're
committed to helping an entire universe.
Countless billions of beings.
Countless billions of animals and other creatures.
And we do have this ability. You do have this power. I pray that you have this power in this lifetime.
I pray that you unleash it in this lifetime.
Your mind already has the ability to reach out to every living being and promise to take care of them.
So the purpose of this lam rim,
the purpose of this retreat [of this course] would be,
to be like traveling in the middle of the sun.
Think of every living being. The
countless beings in a boundless universe.
Get to know them, one by one.
Make a promise to each one of them.
That's what happens
during the first  direct experiences of bodhichitta. It
really happens. It
feels like this.
If you keep imagining
this, it will make this happen.
Really!
So it's up to you whether you want it to happen.
If you really want to be a real bodhisattva,
then practice.
Practice this visualization once or twice a day.
Just when you have a few minutes. Just imagine.
In your imagination, right?
And that will help you trigger this state.
And you will reach bodhichitta. That's why
something like the virus, for that kind of bodhisattva, the virus is not a very important thing.
It's a small thing.
Making money. Making a living.
Feeding your family.
Finding an apartment.
These are incredibly small things. They
're nothing.
Your mind is like...
...your heart is like the middle of the sun.
And a few... I don't know... a few cookies or a few Cokes in the middle of the sun, it doesn't matter. It
's not a thing.  important.
Seek great things!
Everything else becomes small.
And everything else becomes comfortable. Easy.
This is bodhichitta.
Okay!
See you in the next episode.
Episode 10.